Dan Golenpaul Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Dan Golenpaul Papers 1934-1981 (bulk 1934-1977)
MSS59808
Golenpaul, Dan
300 items
2 containers
.8 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Radio and television producer. Correspondence, essays, scripts, contracts, news clippings, and guest lists pertaining to the "Information Please" program produced by Golenpaul for radio and television and to his subsequent publication, Information Please Almanac.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Baruch, Bernard M. (Bernard Mannes), 1870-1965--Correspondence.; Beech, Keyes.; Blum, Léon, 1872-1950--Correspondence.; Fadiman, Clifton, 1904-1999--Correspondence.; Golenpaul, Dan.; Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978--Correspondence.; Kennedy, Edward M. (Edward Moore), 1932-2009--Correspondence.; Kennedy, Edward M. (Edward Moore), 1932-2009.; Keyserling, Leon H. (Leon Hirsch), 1908-1987.; Kieran, John, 1892-1981--Correspondence.; MacLeish, Archibald, 1892-1982.; Muskie, Edmund S., 1914-1996--Correspondence.; Myrdal, Gunnar, 1898-1987--Correspondence.; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962--Correspondence.; Shaw, Bernard, 1856-1950--Correspondence.; Warren, Earl, 1891-1974--Correspondence.
Organizations
Marx Brothers--Correspondence.
Subjects
Radio programs.; Radio scripts.; Television programs.; Television scripts.
Titles
Information Please (Radio program); Information Please (Television program); Information Please Almanac.
Occupations
Radio producers.; Television producers.
Provenance
The papers of Dan Golenpaul, radio and television producer and almanac publisher, were given to the Library of Congress in 1981 by his wife, Ann Golenpaul.
Transfers
Motion picture films and sound recordings have been transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division, where they are identified as part of the Dan Golenpaul Papers. Cartoons have been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division where they are also identified as part of these papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Dan Golenpaul are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Dan Golenpaul (1901-1974) span the years 1934-1981, with the bulk of material dated 1934-1977. The collection includes correspondence, writings, scripts, contracts, clippings, and guest lists relating particularly to the "Information Please" program produced by Golenpaul on radio and television and to his subsequent publication, Information Please Almanac. Material relating to other radio and publishing ventures include correspondence, scripts, clippings, and notes for "The Education of Hyman Kaplan," "Raising Your Parents," "Magazine of the Air," and The First Years in College. Correspondence is arranged alphabetically. Radio show correspondents include "Information Please" performers Clifton Fadiman and John Kieran and other writers or entertainers such as the Marx brothers, Chico, Harpo, and Groucho. Much of the Information Please Almanac correspondence is with political figures, especially with Democrats in the 1960s and early 1970s, such as Hubert H. Humphrey, Edward M. Kennedy, and Edmund S. Muskie. Golenpaul solicited essays for the almanac from international political figures and social commentators, including Léon Blum, Gunnar Myrdal, and George Bernard Shaw, along with Americans such as Bernard Baruch, Eleanor Roosevelt, and Earl Warren. Also included in the papers are essays by Keyes Beech, Edward M. Kennedy, Leon H. Keyserling, and Archibald MacLeish.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by type of material.
Container List
- "Information Please" radio and television show (Box 1)
  - American Tobacco Co. litigation, 1943 (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 1945-1959, 1975, undated (Box 1)
  - Contracts (Box 1)
    - Employment (Box 1)
      - Adams, Franklin, 1938-1949 (Box 1)
      - Fadiman, Clifton, 1938-1949 (Box 1)
      - Kieran, John, 1938-1952 (Box 1)
      - Levant, Oscar, 1939-1940 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1938, 1952-1954 (Box 1)
    - News organizations (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous newspapers, 1954-1956, 1964-1966, (2 folders) (Box 1)
      - New York Herald Tribune, 1954, 1981 (Box 1)
      - Pathé News, 1939-1941 (Box 1)
    - Sponsors, 1944-1952 (Box 1)
  - Guest lists and notes, 1952, undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellany, undated (Box 1)
  - Movie shorts by Pathé News, program ideas and question lists, undated (Box 1)
  - Questions submitted for the show by entertainers and writers, 1937-1940 (Box 1)
  - Scripts and transcripts, 1938-1940, 1952, undated (Box 1)
- Information Please Almanac (Box 2)
  - Correspondence (Box 2)
    - General, 1948-1974 (Box 2)
    - Thank you for complimentary books, 1969-1977 (Box 2)
    - With contributing authors (Box 2)
      - Individuals, 1947-1971, 1976 (Box 2)
      - National representatives (Box 2)
        - France, 1948 (Box 2)
        - Great Britain, 1948 (Box 2)
        - Miscellaneous, 1948 (Box 2)
        - USSR, 1948 (Box 2)
  - Essays by contributors, 1965-1971 (Box 2)
  - Notes on publishing history and clippings, 1947-1975, undated (Box 2)
- Miscellany (Box 2)
  - "Education of Hyman Kaplan," 1937-1938, undated (Box 2)
  - The First Years in College, press notices, 1965 (Box 2)
  - "Magazine of the Air," 1934, 1942 (Box 2)
  - "Raising Your Parents" (Box 2)
    - Correspondence and notes, 1937-1938, undated (Box 2)
    - Scripts, 1936-1937, (2 folders) (Box 2)